<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--*-nxml-*-->
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
    SPDX-License-Identifier: Apache-2.0
    Copyright (c) 2021, Dell Inc. or its subsidiaries.  All rights reserved.
-->
<refentry id="stacd.conf" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <refentryinfo>
        <title>stacd.conf</title>
        <productname>nvme-stas</productname>

        <author>
            <personname>
                <honorific>Mr</honorific>
                <firstname>Martin</firstname>
                <surname>Belanger</surname>
            </personname>

            <affiliation>
                <orgname>Dell, Inc.</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </refentryinfo>

    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>stacd.conf</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>

    <refnamediv>
        <refname>stacd.conf</refname>
        <refpurpose>
            <citerefentry project="man-pages">
                <refentrytitle>stacd</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>
            configuration file
        </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <para>
            <filename>/etc/stas/stacd.conf</filename>
        </para>
    </refsynopsisdiv>

    <refsect1>
        <title>Description</title>

        <para>
            When <citerefentry project="man-pages"><refentrytitle>stacd</refentrytitle>
            <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> starts up, it reads its
            configuration from <filename>stacd.conf</filename>.
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1>
        <title>Configuration File Format</title>
        <para>
            <filename>stacd.conf</filename> is a plain text file divided into
            sections, with configuration entries in the style
            <replaceable>key</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable>.
            Whitespace immediately before or after the <literal>=</literal> is
            ignored. Empty lines and lines starting with <literal>#</literal>
            are ignored, which may be used for commenting.
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1>
        <title>Options</title>

        <refsect2>
            <title>[Global] section</title>
            <para>
                The following options are available in the
                <literal>[Global]</literal>section:
            </para>

            <variablelist>
                <xi:include href="standard-conf.xml" xpointer="tron"/>
                <xi:include href="standard-conf.xml" xpointer="hdr-digest"/>
                <xi:include href="standard-conf.xml" xpointer="data-digest"/>
                <xi:include href="standard-conf.xml" xpointer="kato"/>
                <xi:include href="standard-conf.xml" xpointer="ip-family"/>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><varname>ignore-iface=</varname></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Takes a boolean argument. This option controls how
                            connections with I/O Controllers (IOC) are made.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            There is no guarantee that there will be a route to
                            reach that IOC. However, we can use the socket
                            option SO_BINDTODEVICE to force the connection to be
                            made on a specific interface instead of letting the
                            routing tables decide where to make the connection.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            This option determines whether <code>stacd</code> will use
                            SO_BINDTODEVICE to force connections on an interface
                            or just rely on the routing tables. The default is
                            to use SO_BINDTODEVICE, in other words, <code>stacd</code> does
                            not ignore the interface.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            BACKGROUND:
                            By default, <code>stacd</code> will connect to IOCs on the same
                            interface that was used to retrieve the discovery
                            log pages. If stafd discovers a DC on an interface
                            using mDNS, and stafd connects to that DC and
                            retrieves the log pages, it is expected that the
                            storage subsystems listed in the log pages are
                            reachable on the same interface where the DC was
                            discovered.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            For example, let's say a DC is discovered on
                            interface ens102. Then all the subsystems listed in
                            the log pages retrieved from that DC must be
                            reachable on interface ens102. If this doesn't work,
                            for example you cannot "ping -I ens102 [storage-ip]",
                            then the most likely explanation is that arp proxy
                            is not enabled on the switch that the host is
                            connected to on interface ens102. Whatever you do,
                            resist the temptation to manually set up the routing
                            tables or to add alternate routes going over a
                            different interface than the one where the DC is
                            located. That simply won't work. Make sure arp proxy
                            is enabled on the switch first.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            Setting routes won't work because, by default, <code>stacd</code>
                            uses the SO_BINDTODEVICE socket option when it
                            connects to IOCs. This option is used to force a
                            socket connection to be made on a specific interface
                            instead of letting the routing tables decide where
                            to connect the socket. Even if you were to manually
                            configure an alternate route on a different interface,
                            the connections (i.e. host to IOC) will still be
                            made on the interface where the DC was discovered by
                            stafd.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            Defaults to <literal>false</literal>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><varname>udev-rule=</varname></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Takes a string argument <literal>enabled</literal> or
                            <literal>disabled</literal>. This option determines
                            whether nvme-cli's udev rule will be executed
                            or ignored.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            A udev rule gets intalled with <code>nvme-cli</code>
                            that tells the udev daemon (<code>udevd</code>) to look
                            for Asychronous Event Notifications (AEN) indicating
                            a change of discovery log page entries (DPLE). The
                            udev rule is installed as: <filename>/usr/lib/udev/rules.d/70-nvmf-autoconnect.rules</filename>
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            When an AEN is detected, <code>udevd</code> simply
                            instructs <code>systemd</code> to start a one-shot
                            service that will retrieve the changed DPLEs and
                            connect to all the I/O Contollers (IOC) listed in
                            the DPLEs. This is basically the same as perfoming
                            <code>nvme-cli</code>'s "<code>connect-all</code>"
                            command.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            Unfortunately, <code>stafd</code> and <code>stacd</code>
                            also perform the same operations when an AEN is received.
                            This results in a race condition between <code>udevd</code>
                            and <code>stafd</code>/<code>stacd</code>.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            This is not really a problem. <code>stafd</code> and
                            <code>stacd</code> are designed to handle this type
                            of race condition and will conclude, eventually, that
                            the connections succeeded. The only downside is that
                            there may be error messages printed to the syslog
                            when the race condition happens. These messages are
                            printed by the kernel because two processes are trying
                            to connect to the same IOC at the same time. One of
                            them will be rejected by the kernel, but the other
                            will succeed.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            The <code>udev-rule</code> option allows a user to
                            disable nvme-cli's udev rule so that <code>udevd</code> will
                            not take action on received AENs. Instead, only
                            <code>stafd</code>/<code>stacd</code> will be allowed
                            to react to AENs and set up IOC connections.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            Defaults to <literal>enabled</literal>, which means
                            that <code>udevd</code> and <code>stafd</code>/<code>stacd</code>
                            will react to AENs. It also means that the race condition
                            will happen by default and error messages will be
                            printed to the syslog.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term><varname>sticky-connections=</varname></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Takes a string argument <literal>enabled</literal> or
                            <literal>disabled</literal>. This option determines
                            whether connections to I/O controllers will be
                            maintained after Discovery Log Page Entry (DLPE)
                            removal.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            Zoning configuration is performed at Discovery
                            Controllers (DC). A zone is used to specify the list
                            of I/O controllers that a host is allowed to access.
                            The zone contains a list of hosts and the I/O controllers
                            that these hosts can access. Users can add or
                            remove I/O controllers and/or hosts from zones.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            DCs notify hosts of zoning configuration changes by
                            sending Asynchronous Event Notifications (AEN)
                            indicating a "Change of Discovery Log Page (DLP)".
                            The host uses these AENs as a trigger to retrieve the
                            new list of DLPEs (i.e. I/O controllers) by issuing a
                            Get DLP command. This happens in real time, which
                            means that a host that was previously connected
                            to an I/O controller may suddenly be told that it is
                            no longer allowed to connect to that I/O controller
                            and should disconnect from it.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            The parameter <code>sticky-connections</code>
                            determines how <code>stacd</code> reacts to the
                            removal of an I/O controller DLPE. In other
                            words, whether it should immediately disconnect
                            from I/O controllers when the DPLE is removed,
                            or whether it should maintain the connection.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            Note that <code>nvme-stas</code> was modeled after
                            <code>nvme-cli</code>. <code>nvme-cli</code> maintains
                            I/O controller connections by default (i.e. connections
                            are sticky). That's why <code>nvme-stas</code> also
                            maintains I/O controller connections by default.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            With <code>sticky-connections=enabled</code>, the default,
                            <code>stacd</code> does not disconnect from I/O
                            controllers when a DPLE is removed. Instead, users
                            can issue the <code>nvme-cli</code> command
                            "<code>nvme disconnect</code>" to disconnect (or wait
                            until the next system reboot at which time all
                            connections will be removed).
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            With <code>sticky-connections=disabled</code>,
                            <code>stacd</code> immediately disconnects from
                            a previously connected I/O controller if the response
                            to a Get DLP command no longer contains a DLPE
                            matching that I/O controller.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect2>

        <xi:include href="standard-conf.xml" xpointer="controller"/>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1>
        <title>See Also</title>
        <para>
            <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>stacd</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>
        </para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>
